Edwin Augustus Porcher Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Drawings, Series I
  - Drawings from the HMS Cleopatra
    - 14. Hong Kong. HMS Cleopatra lying off Jardine's establishment. November 22, 1852., 1852 November 22; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Over
      Jardine & Matheson Co. were the most powerful opium merchants in Hong Kong. They founded their company in 1832, grew rapidly by exporting tea and silk to England, and by smuggling opium. They purchased land in the Causeway area when Britain acquired Hong Kong after the Treaty of Nanking, at the conclusion of the first opium war. Porcher's journal describes the "patent slip" at Jardine's Establishment, where "ships of about 500 tons… can be hauled up" and repaired (6). A drawing of the purchase for hauling the vessels is included on page 7 (diary).
      Watercolors; Hong Kong (China); Cleopatra (Ship: 1843); Jardine, Matheson & Co.
    - 15. HMS Cleopatra at anchor off the dockyard. Dec. 24, 1852., 1852 December 24; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.5 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22217
      Watercolors; Cleopatra (Ship: 1843)
    - 16. Stone-cutters Island. Man of war junk in the foreground and the main land of China in the distance. October 1851., 1851 October; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 226 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22218
      Watercolors; Junks; Stonecutters Island (Hong Kong)
    - 17. Joss house built in Tai-Pin-Shan in 1851. August 7, 1852., 1852 August 7; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      "Joss House" was the derogatory term used by the British to refer to Chinese temples. The word "Joss" was derived from the Portuguese deos or God, adapted in the pidgin trading language at Chinese ports (Whitworth 463-464). Tai Ping Shan means "peace hill" and was named after the area's peaceful settlement after the conclusion of an 1810 sea battle between pirates and Qing Dynasty warships. This peace was interrupted when British warships arrived, and the street became a traditional Chinese enclave in the Victoria Peak region otherwise dominated by the British garrison. Taoist, Confucian and Buddhist worshippers happily co-mingled along the street, and Porcher's view likely depicts the temple devoted to "Jai Kung", or "poor man's Buddha", constructed in 1851 as a temporary repository for the stone tablets of Hong Kong's deceased, whose remains were far from their ancestral burial grounds. A statue of the god Tai Chong Wong presided over the souls of the deceased (Ingham 107-109).
      The image of the Chinese barber may have been inspired by the work of George Chinnery (1774-1852), who completed several sketches and at least one oil of the subject.
      B1977.14.22219
      Watercolors; Hong Kong (China); Temples -- China
    - 18. Joss house on the Island of Hap-Lee-Chow (Duck's tongue) opposite Shek-Pai- Wan (Aberdeen). December 31, 1852., 1852 December 31; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Shek-Pai-Wan is a bay between Hong Kong and Aberdeen Island. The British were initially attracted to waterfall at Aberdeen because it was a source of fresh water supply. A short journey from Aberdeen, Hap-Lee-Chow (Ap Lei Chau Island) was an important maritime center. Temples (called "Joss Houses" by the British) were important places of prayer for local fishermen, who would give offerings to ensure plentiful catches (Ingham 142).
      B1977.14.22220
      Watercolors; Temples -- China; Shek Pai Wan (Hong Kong, China); Ap Lei Chau (Hong Kong, China)
    - 19. Hong Kong. Village and barracks at Check-Chow (Stanley) on the S.W. side of the island. December 31, 1852., 1852 December 31; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 24 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      In his diary, Porcher describes the British barracks built on the 'Checkchu' (or 'Check-chow') peninsula (called Stanley) and at Siwan: "[A]fter a certain time, all the English troops were obliged to be called in in consequence of both places turning out so unhealthy, on account of the malaria rising from the valleys, over which both stations had been built, at present 12 and 15 men of the Ceylon Rifles under the command of Native Officers, having been left there" (Diary 3).
      B1977.14.22221
      Chek Chue (China); Watercolors; Hong Kong (China)
    - 20. Attack on a piratical fleet in Byas's Bay on June 25th 1851., 1851 June 25; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Porcher's image (or another version of it) was adapted for publication in the Illustrated London News, October 4, 1851, which reported an "Attack on Chinese Pirates by the Boats of Her majesty's Ship 'Cleopatra,'" (402). On June 24th, the Superintendent of the police received news that fishermen at Mir's Bay had been attacked by a fleet of junks led by "Shap-'ng-tchi" (Shap-ng-tsai, the infamous pirate). Captain Massie of the Cleopatra ordered the barge, cutter, and pinnace (manned by Porcher and Hon. C. Crofton) armed and deployed. When the pirate junks were sighted near Bias Bay, a five hour chase ensued.
      Three junks were run up to the head of the bay and driven on shore, while their escaping crews ran into the hills. "Weichow and Tamshuy" were taken as prisoners to the Victoria Gaol. The Friend of India (quoted in the Illustrated London News ) praises Lieutenants Price and Porcher: "Starting with only one day's provisions and water, they pulled and sailed, with a midsummer sun over them, for a good part of twenty-four hours before they came up with the enemy; and then, almost sick from exhaustion… they commenced a cannonade and fusillade upon three vessels, mounting eighteen guns apiece, and otherwise armed to the teeth, sufficient to have blown them out of the water with a single broadside – they continued that attack until nearly all the powder was expended… Throughout this encounter there was only one casualty; Lieutenant Price being slightly wounded with a spent shot. The sails of the boats have suffered the most, and bear sufficiently honourable testimony to the severity of the encounter" ( Illustrated London News 402). The scale of the Cleopatra's ships are enhanced in the published version, and positioned on either side of the junk for dramatic effect. The Royal Navy's destruction of pirate fleets was controversial, as the monetary rewards ("head money") distributed to officers was seen as a questionable private motivation. Concern was raised over the deaths of innocent people on board (captives of pirates).
      B1977.14.22222
      Naval battles; Junks; Pirates; Watercolors; Daya Bay (China)
    - 21. Amoy with part of the island of Ku-Lang-Su taken from the outer anchorage of Cornwallis' Rock. June 3rd, 1852., 1852 June 3; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 23 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      As Porcher notes in his diary, Amoy (today called Xiamen) was the most important harbor in the province of Fujian and was dominated by foreign trade at the turn of the 18th century. The island of Kulang Su (Gulangyu), on the western side of Xiamen's harbor, was once occupied by British troops after the capture of the city in 1841 until it was restored to Chinese in 1845 (Nield 99). Its five British batteries are still visible in Porcher's view. In his diary, he expounds the strategic advantages of this location: "In case of another misunderstanding with the Chinese the island of Kulang-su would be well adapted for a settlement, the channel between it and Amoy being only 672 yards wide – the ridge of hills on the island being higher than those opposite. There are two distinct ridges which might be separately defended, the highest point being 280 feet above the sea. The island is principally granite, and the soil being formed of it in a decomposed state…. Fresh water from wells are plentiful, and artificial channels conduct it to boats" (53).
      B1977.14.22223
      Xiamen Shi (China); Watercolors; Gulangyu Qu (Xiamen Shi, China)
    - 22. A suspicious looking lorcha detained by HMS Hermes in Blenheim Reach, Whampoa on June 26th 1852., 1852 June 26; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 19 x 29 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Whampoa was the way-station between Macau and Canton before the institution of the treaty port system. It was a popular subject among European and Chinese export artists, as foreign ships would anchor there before sending goods on smaller boats to Canton. A typical merchant ship's journey up the Pearl River Delta would first dock at Macau, then to Lintin Island, then travelling onwards through the estuary of the Bocca Tigris (Human), finally anchoring at Whampoa. In 1844, Chinese authorities proposed rules to prevent smuggling via Portuguese lorchas, requiring they bear registration numbers and report for examination. Lorchas had been involved in the importation of cannon for native insurgents and sometimes passed themselves off as British (Perdue, n.p.).
      B1977.14.22224
      Lorchas; Huangpu Qu (Guangzhou Shi, China); Watercolors; Hermes (Ship: 1835)
    - 23. My cabin in H.M.S. Cleopatra, from April 1849, to Sept. 1853., 1849 April - 1853 September; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 20 x 29 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22225
      Watercolors; Cleopatra (Ship: 1843); Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878
    - 24. Philippine Islands. Principal bridge at Manila. March 8th 1851., 1851 March 8; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      This view of Manila shows daily life in the bustling port city. The bridge is in the district of Binondo, an enclave of ethnic Chinese and the main commercial center amongst Chinese mestizos and Spanish Filipinos (Abinales 79).
      B1977.14.22226
      Manila (Philippines); Binondo (Manila, Philippines); Watercolors
    - 25. Official visit of the boats of the Cleopatra to the Pangeran Madoud's house, at Mengatal on January 31st 1851. The mountain of Kini Balu in the distance., 1851 January 31; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      On September 12, 1851, the HMS Dolphin was attacked in Maladu Bay by Illanun pirates. Captain Robertson and Supercargo Robert Burns (grandson of the poet) and the crew were murdered by pirates from Tunku. In response, the Cleopatra, Semiramis and Pluto were dispatched from Singapore on January 10th and arrived at Labuan by the 20th, sailing on to Mengatal to hold a meeting with local ruler Pangeran Madand about bartering with the Iranun (Illanun) Pirates and providing them a boat. A "Mr. Melrum" accompanied the diplomatic party to negotiate the repayment of a debt (see Porcher's diary, page 30). Porcher depicts the British crews firing a salute upon arrival at the Pangeran Madand's village.
      B1977.14.22227
      Pirates; Menggatal (Malaysia); Watercolors
    - 26. Borneo. The government offices at Labuan. March 1st 1852., 1852 March 1; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      The island of Labuan was taken possession by the British in 1846, and proposed as a British base against piracy in the South China Sea. It became a crown colony in 1848. Porcher indicates that the island's most important product was coal, and describes at length the island's position, crops, cultivation and harbor (diary 20-28). He also includes a detailed map of Labuan.
      B1977.14.22228
      Maps; Labuan; Watercolors
    - 27. Borneo. Skirmish with the Illanoon Pirates at Tooncoo on February 16th 1852., 1852 February 16; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      The incident Porcher depicts was reported in the Nautical Magazine and Naval Chronicle for 1852 (222-223). Porcher and the crew of the Cleopatra, Pluto and Semiramis were traveling up the Tunku river in pursuit of the Illanun [Iranun] pirates responsible for the murder of the HMS Dolphin's crew (see "25. Official visit of the Boats of the Cleopatra to the Pangeran Madoud's house"). When they arrived at the residence of Rajah Muda, marines and armed men landed to find white flags hoisted on the roof of the houses. Porcher reports: "In retaliation for their having fired at us the day before, when white flags were flying, both at the Chief's house, and also in our boats, about 40 houses were burned, and the little property that was found in them destroyed, as well as their paddy, fruit trees, etc." (34). The pirates returned fire again, killing one man and wounding two others. Porcher continues with a detailed description of the Iranun pirates from Mindanao, who were known for murdering crews of vessels "except those they are able to sell as slaves". The entire landscape is frenetic with action; figures are hiding behind foliage with guns, while gunfire issues from the British vessels in the river.
      B1977.14.2229
      Pirates; Naval battles; Watercolors
    - 28. Pinang from the anchorage. December 1851., 1851 December; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, heightened with white, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 23 x 26 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm > (Box Oversize 1)
      Penang, an island off the coast of the Malaysian Peninsula, was first occupied by the British East India Company in 1786, and became a British 'Straits Settlement" along with Province Wellesley, Malacca and Singapore when the Anglo-Dutch Treaty (1824) brought these under the administration of the British East Company. It became an important trading center under the British, its commercial architecture dotting the shoreline of Porcher's watercolor.
      B1977.14.22230
      Watercolors; Pulau Pinang (Malaysia: State)
    - 29. A Malay village at Pinang. December 22nd 1851., 1851 December 22; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22231
    - 30. Singapore. General view of the town. November 1851., 1851 November; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 24.5 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Singapore is at the crossroads of Indian and Pacific Oceans, the Malacca, Sunda and Lombok Straits, and the South China Seas, which made it a key trading center in the India-China route. This view overlooking the Singapore River was taken from an observation point on Mount Wallich, named after Nathaniel Wallich who founded the settlement's Botanical and Experimental Garden. Today the view is no longer replicable, as Mount Wallich was levelled in 1885. Significantly, Porcher's view pre-dates one of the most well-known panoramic paintings of this viewpoint by Percy Carpenter, Singapore from Mount Wallich, 1856. Many of the same structures are visible in both the Porcher and Carpenter: Government Hill and Governor's House, the colonial residence built in 1822 by G.D. Coleman, which itself provided the colonial administration with an uninterrupted view (most view of Singapore were commissioned from this vantage point). The elevated vantage point also eliminated the unattractive mangrove swamps that dominated low-lying areas. The spires of the Armenian Church of St. Gregory the Illuminator and the Cathedral of the Good Shepherd; the broad esplanade of Telok Ayer street; the Telok Ayer market, also built after designs by Coleman, on the spit of land jutting into the basin (Pieris 43-45; Wong and Waterson 96).
      B1977.14.22232
      Watercolors; Singapore; Telok Ayer (District: Singapore)
    - 31. The river at Singapore. November 1851. Lithographed., Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Government Hill features prominently in views of Singapore, often as the apex of the composition, as Porcher has done in this view from the South Boat Quay near the junction with Market Street. Raffles had established his presence and political control by appropriating the traditional elevated domain of the Malay Rulers, who occupied it (then called Bukit Larangan 'Forbidden Hill') in the fourteenth century (Wong 37). In Porcher's view, the river is bustling with traffic: small sampans ferry passengers to the arched landing and a Malay perahu-mayang fishing boat brings in its catch at lower right. A number of warehouses lining the banks of the river are accessible by the Thomson's Bridge – the only access to the commercial town. Porcher labeled the Master Attendant's building (at right), which was the headquarters of the Master Attendant of the British entrepot and a post office. In a lithographed version of Porcher's view by Vincent Brooks, a nakhoda (boat captain) was added in the foreground, and a Javanese trading vessel at left. Several boats filled with cargo, and a display of tropical fruits perched dockside entices viewers to the 'exotic' goods flowing in and out of the port (see Hong Suen Wong page 72 for Vincent Brooks lithograph).
      B1977.14.22233
      Singapore; Watercolors; Singapore River (Singapore)
    - 32. Pepper grown at Sinapore [sic]. November 4th 1851., 1851 November 4; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount.; sheet 11.5 x 16 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Mounted together with "33. Coffee from Pinang. May 28th 1850." "34. Cloves from Pinang. Dec. 22nd 1851." "35. Nutmegs from Pinang. June 1st 1850."
      B1977.14.22234
      Watercolors; Peppers; Singapore
    - 33. Coffee from Pinang. May 28th 1850., 1850 May 28; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 9.5 x 16 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm > (Box Oversize 1)
      Mounted together with "32. Pepper Grown at Sinapore. November 4th 1851.," "34. Cloves from Pinang. Dec. 22nd 1851.," "35. Nutmegs from Pinang. June 1st 1850."
      B1977.14.22235
      Coffee; Watercolors; Pulau Pinang (Malaysia: State)
    - 34. Cloves from Pinang. Dec. 22nd 1851., 1851 December 22; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 12.4 x 16.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Mounted together with "32. Pepper Grown at Sinapore. [sic] November 4th 1851.," "33. Coffee from Pinang. May 28th 1850.," "35. Nutmegs from Pinang. June 1st 1850."
      B1977.14.22236
      Pulau Pinang (Malaysia: State); Clove (Spice); Watercolors
    - 35. Nutmegs from Pinang. June 1st 1850., 1850 June 1; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 12 x 17.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      Mounted together with "32. Pepper Grown at Sinapore. [sic] November 4th 1851.," "33. Coffee from Pinang. May 28th 1850.," "34. Cloves from Pinang. Dec. 22nd 1851."
      B1977.14.22237
      Watercolors; Nutmeg (Spice); Pulau Pinang (Malaysia: State)
    - 63. Coryphoena Hippurus. A small dolphin weighing 4 lbs, caught in Latitude 5˚S, Longitude 16˚W. August 8, 1853., 1853 August 8; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 22 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 1)
      B1977.14.22238
      Dolphinfishes; Watercolors
  - Drawings from the HMS Hibernia
    - 56. H.M. gun boat schooner Kertch, off Malta. Sept. 22. 1859., 1859 September 22; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 35.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      The gun boat Kertch is pictured flying the white ensign. Porcher requested to use this vessel for his Cyrene expedition but was not permitted for use by the Admiralty.
      B1977.14.22182
      Watercolors; Malta; Kertch (Ship)
    - 57. A market boat leaving Gozo for Malta. September 28, 1860., 1860 September 28; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 25.25 x 35.5 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      B1977.14.22199
      Merchant ships; Gozo Island (Malta); Watercolors
    - 58. Malta. Entrance of the Grand Harbour. March 6. 1858., 1858 March 6; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      The Grand Harbour was the cultural, administrative and business center of the island. The Order of St. John urbanized the space around the Harbour in the 16th century, and Valletta was constructed as the capital of the islands following the Ottoman Siege of 1564. As the administrative core of the Matese islands, Valletta's city planners stressed efficiency and centralization (Cassar 125-6).
      B1977.14.221571
      Grand Harbour (Malta); Valletta (Malta); Malta; Watercolors
    - 59. Fort St. Angelo from the rocks round Fort Ricasoli. Dec. 17, 1857., 1857 December 17; Porcher, Edwin Augustus, 1824-1878; 1 drawing: watercolor, body color, on medium-thick beige paper, affixed to card mount; sheet 26 x 36 cm, mount 36.5 x 52 cm (Box Oversize 2)
      "In fine, it may be said that Malta is as defensible as nature and art combined can render it" (Martin 159). Fort St. Angelo, also known as Castrum Marus, was first constructed in 878 AD as an Arab fortification and was built up by successive waves of invaders, and became the headquarters of the Grand Master. The structure withstood attack during the Ottoman siege of 1565, acting as the center of resistance and was later occupied by the British Army (Jackson 72-6).
      B1977.14.22156
      Malta; Watercolors; Fortification; Grand Harbour (Malta); Knights of Malta. Fort St. Angelo (Birgu, Malta)